Finding aid for the Edward Nicholas and Dollie Ann Cole papers
Bentley Historical Library
Edward Nicholas and Dollie Ann Cole papers
1829-2016
1960-1977
Bentley Historical Library
Cole, Edward Nicholas, 1909-1977
88180 Aa 2 UAl
19 linear feet
2 oversize boxes
1 film reels
1 oversize folder
Edward (Ed) Nicholas Cole was a President of General Motors Corporation and highly influential automotive engineer. His wife Dollie Ann was a well-known philanthropist and socialite in Michigan and Texas. Collection include correspondence, reports, technical records, speech transcripts, genealogical papers, photographs, audiovisual materials and scrapbooks.
Donated by Joan A. Caine Hoelaars (donor no. 7414 ).
Additional materials were donated by David Cole (donor no. 11441 ) in February 2016 and the Estate of Dollie Ann Cole (donor no. 11483 ), received in in two accessions in April 2016.
The collection is open without restriction.
Edward "Ed" Nicholas "Ed" Cole was born in 1909 to a farming family in Marne, Michigan. Cole began tinkering with motors, electricity and other mechanical devices from a young age. After a year at Grand Rapids Junior College, in 1930 he transferred to the General Motors Institute in Flint, a cooperative education program General Motors (GM) used to develop engineers and managers. While in school, Cole demonstrated clear engineering aptitude and went on to begin his professional career in the Cadillac Division of the company.
Cole quickly rose through the ranks at Cadillac and during World War II was named Chief Design Engineer for light tanks and combat vehicles. After the war, he was named Chief Engineer (1946) and Works Manager (1950) at Cadillac and was responsible for overseeing operations at the Cadillac light tank factory in Cleveland during the Korean War. In 1952, Cole was named Chief Engineer at Chevrolet and in 1956 became the General Manager of Chevrolet and a Vice-President of General Motors.
While at Chevrolet, Cole was responsible for many significant innovations that shaped the automobile industry. He was member of the team that developed the first Corvette sports car and is known as the "father" of the Chevy small block V8 engine. The engine was a major technological advancement due to it's small size, power and affordable production and continues to influence automotive engineering today. Cole was named to the Board of Directors of General Motors in 1961.
One Cole's most significant projects as general manager of Chevrolet was the development of the Chevrolet Corvair, the company's first entrance into the burgeoning "compact car" market. Released in 1960, the Corvair was an early commercial success and lauded for its engineering and design innovations. Cole was pictured on the cover of Time Magazine in 1959 and the Corvair was named the 1960 "Car of the Year" by Motor Trends magazine. In 1965, the Corvair was highlighted in Ralph Nader's landmark book "Unsafe at Any Speed", which accused General Motors of compromising on consumer safety to develop cheaper and faster cars. Cole publicly refuted Nader's criticisms of the design of the Corvair and the debate led to the creation of the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration and a new focus on consumer safety in the industry.
In 1967, Cole was appointed President of General Motors, a position he served in until his retirement in 1974. As president, he oversaw the development of Chevrolet Vega, instituted an increased emphasis on consumer safety and was a pioneer in considering environmental impact of automobiles. In the early 1970s, Cole anticipated the establishment of stronger federal regulations against exhaust emissions. He led GM engineers in developing engines with lower compression rates and introduced the automotive catalytic converter. The design used unleaded gasoline which is significantly less harmful to both humans and the environment than traditional leaded gasoline. The catalytic converter helped reduce exhaust emissions while improving fuel economy and is considered a pivotal automotive engineering development.
A prodigious worker, Cole was granted 18 separate patents before his retirement from General Motors in 1974. After retirment, he became Chairman and CEO of the Checkers Motor Corporation, a Kalamazoo, Michigan company that produced taxicabs. Cole was also the Chairman of International Husky, a partnership with Boeing that looked to pioneer the heavy duty air freight industry. In 1977, Cole was killed in a private plane crash over Kalamazoo. He was survived by his wife, Dollie Ann Cole, and five children including his son from his first marriage, David E. Cole, a University of Michigan alumni and chairman of the Center for Automotive Research.
Dollie Ann Cole was born in 1930 in Fort Worth, Texas and attended the University of Texas. She married Ed Cole in 1963. Dollie Cole became well known in the automotive industry for her style and outspoken and vivacious personality which included once calling into the Phil Donahue Show to defend General Motors against criticism from a supporter of Ralph Nader. The production of the first GM cars equipped with airbags was attributed to Cole asking her husband to design a safety solution that would accommodate her fur coats better than lap seatbelts. She took an active interest in the auto industry and in 1972 was the first woman to ride in the pace car at the Indianapolis 500.
Dollie Cole was a featured columnist for the Saturday Evening Post and made several appearances on radio and television shows of the day. She was heavily involved in charity work, serving as the Vice Chairman of the Smithsonian Air and Space Museum, director of National Corvette Museum, a board member of the Public Broadcasting Service and was involved in local Michigan organizations. After Ed Cole's death in 1977, she moved to the Briarpatch Ranch near Austin, Texas where she was a fixture in local society and continued to be involved in community and charity work. Dollie Ann Cole passed away in 2014.
The Edward Nicholas and Dollie Ann Cole papers contain materials from influential automotive exectuive Edward Nicholas Cole and his wife Dollie Ann Cole. The collection has been organized into two series:
The Edward Nicholas Cole series contains correspondence, business records, reports, photographs, audiovisual materials, transcripts, and blueprints. The series has been divided into four subseries: the Correspondence subseries contains personal and professional letters, the Project Files subseries includes documents related to Cole's career with General Motors, Chevrolet, Checker Motors Corporation and other projects. The Speeches and Appearences subseries chronicles Cole's public speaking engagements in the early 1970s and the Personal Materials subseries contains photographs, audiovisual materials and other materials related to Cole's family and recreational interests.
The Dollie Ann Cole series contains correspondence, papers, photographs and scrapbooks. The series has been organized into two subseries: the Correspondence series which contains letters dated between 1968-1976 and the Topical files series which includes materials related to Cole's charitable and community work, her media appearances and other pursuits.
Automobile industry.; Automobile industry executives -- Michigan.; Automobiles -- Design and construction.; Chevrolet automobile.; Corvair automobile.; General Motors automobiles.; Philanthropists -- Women.; Film reels.; Phonograph records.; Photo albums.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings.; Cole, Edward Nicholas, 1909-1977.; Cole, Dollie Ann.; Cole, Dollie Ann.; Checker Motor Corp. (Kalamazoo, Mich.); General Motors Corporation.; General Motors Corporation. Cadillac Motor Car Division.; General Motors Corporation. Chevrolet Motor Division.; General Motors Corporation. Engineering Department.
- Edward Nicholas Cole, 1829-1997
  The Edward Nicholas Cole series contains correspondence, reports, project documents, blueprints, photographs, speech transcripts and audiovisual materials. The series has been divided into four sub-series:
  The Correspondence subseries (2 linear feet) includes personal and professional letters dated between 1952-1977. Subjects include Cole's promotion to President of General Motors, his 1974 automobile safety debate with Ralph Nader and hobbies such as his work with the Boy Scouts of America.
  The Project Files subseries (4 linear feet, 1 oversize box, and 1 tube) contains professional papers related to Cole's work with General Motors, Chevrolet, Checker Motors Corporation, International Husky Inc, and other projects. The materials highlight his accomplished and diverse career and include pictures of the light tanks he developed for Cadillac during World War II, audiovisual materials about the Chevrolet Corvette and Corvair cars and preliminary blueprints of new designs for Checker Motors Corporation. Other materials of interest include a series of project plans, feasibility studies, financial analyses and other documents related to International Husky Inc, an experimental collaboration with Boeing Aircraft to develop a heavy-duty air freight system.
  The Speeches and Appearances subseries (5 linear feet) contains materials related to Cole's public speaking engagements. In the early 1970s, Cole was often invited to speak at conferences, meetings, commencements and the openings of factories, car dealerships and other buildings. Materials include speech transcripts, itineraries and other scheduling information related to these events.
  The Personal Materials subseries (3 linear feet, 1 oversize box) contains papers, photographs, photo albums and audiovisual materials related to Cole's personal life and family. Materials also include a series of genealogical papers compliled by Joan Hoelaars which document the history of the Cole family.
  - Correspondence, 1952-1977
    - General Correspondence
      - 1952-1963 (Box 1)
      - 1961 (Box 1)
      - 1961-1975 (Box 1)
      - 1964-1968 (Box 1)
      - 1968-1974 (Box 1)
      - 1969 (Box 1)
      - 1970 (Box 1)
      - 1972 (Box 1)
      - 1973 (Box 1)
      - 1974 (Box 1)
      - 1977 (Box 2)
    - Congratulatory Letters
      - A-C, 1963-1967 (Box 2)
      - D-F, 1963-1967 (Box 2)
      - G-K, 1963-1967 (Box 2)
      - H-P, 1964-1967 (Box 2)
      - Q-Z, 1967 (Box 2)
      - Misc, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Topical Correspondence
      - Boy Scouts of America, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
      - Bob Bowman (Aquative Weed Control), undated (Box 2)
      - Campaign Contributions: Barry Goldwater, John Glenn, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Victor Ruether, 1970 (Box 2)
      - Ralph Nader Debate, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Project Files, 1943-1977
    - General Motors
      - Monday Morning News Conference, 1972; 1 videotape (Box 13)
      - Sebring Race, 1956; 1 film reels (Box 16)
      - Attachments to Statement to the Senate Public Works Committee, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Citizen Band Equipment, 1964 (Box 2)
      - Directory, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Environmental Improvement, 1970 (Box 2)
      - European Trip Itinerary, 1969 (Box 2)
      - RRC- Hydrazine Fueled Car Project, 1975 (Box 2)
      - Hydrogen Engine, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Patents, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
      - Patents, 1975 (Box 2)
      - Philippines Trip, undated (Box 2)
      - Summary of General Motors Proposal to Colorado's RTD, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Misc Papers, undated (Box 2)
      - Notebooks
        - European Trip, 1965 (Box 3)
        - Executive Review Notebooks, 1967 (Box 3)
        - President's Dealer Advisory Council, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
        - President's Dealer Advisory Council, 1966-1974 (Box 3)
        - Car Performance Data Notebook, 1972 (Box 3)
        - Misc Notebooks, 1970-1973 (Box 3)
        - Misc Notebooks, 1968 (Box 3)
        - Misc Notebooks, undated (Box 3)
      - Photographs
        - Cadillac WWII Tanks, 1943 (Box 3)
        - Military Photographs, undated (Box 3)
        - Cadillac Tank Photos, 1942 (Box 4)
        - Misc Photographs, undated (Box 4)
        - GM Photo Albums (Box 19)
      - GM Management Conference Scrapbook (Box 19)
    - Chevrolet
      - "Forward with Chevrolet" Report, 1958 (Box 4)
      - "The Greatest Show on Worth" Picture Book, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Interview about C.F. Kettering, 1961 (Box 4)
      - Notepads, undated (Box 4)
      - Audio Recordings
        - Philadelphia Auto Show Interviews, 1959; 1 phonograph record (long-playing records) (Box 18)
        - Designs for You, 1957; 1 phonograph record (long-playing records) (Box 18)
        - "The Best New-Car Two-Car Market!", undated; 1 phonograph record (long-playing records) (Box 18)
        - Zora Arkus-Duntov: "I have a Corvette", undated; 1 phonograph record (long-playing records) (Box 18)
        - Chevrolet: Season's Best, undated; 1 phonograph record (long-playing records) (Box 18)
        - United Foundations, undated; 1 phonograph record (long-playing records) (Box 18)
        - Chevrolet: 2 Top Tunes for, 1958; 1 phonograph record (Box 18)
        - Automotive Report: Corvair, 1959; 1 phonograph record (long-playing records) (Box 18)
        - Automotive Report: Chevrolet, 1961; 1 phonograph record (long-playing records) (Box 18)
        - Jac LeGoff Automobile Show of the Air, 1958; 1 phonograph record (long-playing records) (Box 18)
        - "Designs for You", 1 phonograph record (long-playing records) (Box 18)
      - Films
        - The Experimental Chevrolet Corvette, undated; 1 film reels (Box 17)
        - Corvette SS, Sebring, 1957; 1 film reels (Box 16)
        - Phoenix Rodeo, 1955; 1 film reels (Box 16)
        - American Look, 1958; 1 film reels (Reel 1)
        - POR TS Car, 1963; 1 film reels (Box 17)
        - Sebring Race, 1956; 1 film reels (Box 16)
        - Corvair Testing, undated; 1 film reels (Box 16)
      - Scrapbook Pages, 1956 (Box 10)
      - Scrapbook Pages, 1964 (Box 10)
    - International Husky
      - Boeing Business Considerations, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Business Files, undated (Box 4)
      - Configuration Study: Back-Up Date, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Configuration Update, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Dedicated Air Freight Distribution System, 1973 (Box 4)
      - "The Evolution of Husky", 1972 (Box 4)
      - Financial Statements, 1974 (Box 4)
      - "The Husky Story", undated (Box 4)
      - Iran, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Joint Study Project, undated (Box 4)
      - Middle East Trip undated, 1974 (Box 4)
      - Management Advisory Services, undated (Box 4)
      - Profit Optimization Technique, 1974 (Box 4)
      - Status Report, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Work Statement for Product Definition Phase, 1973 (Box 5)
      - Misc Files, 1973-1975 (Box 5)
      - Husky Dedicated Air Freight Distribution System logistics poster, undated (Box 14)
      - Posters of Airplane Design (Folder 1)
    - Checker Motors Corporation
      - Blueprints and Drawing, undated (Box 5)
      - Board of Directors Press Release, undated (Box 5)
      - Contract Production Capabilities, undated (Box 5)
      - Securities and Exchange Commission Annual Report, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Other Projects
      - Environmental Research Institute of Michigan
        - Memos and Documents, 1974-1976 (Box 5)
        - Board Minutes, 1974-1976 (Box 5)
        - Board Minutes, 1976 (Box 5)
      - Conference on Human Environment, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Pirahna Products, 1976 (Box 5)
      - Unlabeled Drawings, undated (Box 5)
      - Kuwait Hydrazine Project Proposal, undated (Box 5)
      - Misc Notebook, undated (Box 5)
  - Speeches and Appearences, 1969-1975
    - 1969-1971
      - Jack Harris Show (WJR), 1969; 1 audiotape (7.5 ips) (Box 13)
        (Audiovisual Materials)
      - Society of Automotive Engineers of Mid-Michigan, 1970 (Box 5)
      - GMRL Symposium on Emissions, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Detroit Athletic Club, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Bloomfield Hills- Andover High School, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Detroit Masonic Meeting, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Greater Bristol Area Chamber of Commerce, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Automotive Service Industry Association, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Georgia Tech, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Luncheon with Congressmen, Washington D.C., 1971 (Box 5)
      - Central Foundry, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Automotive Warehouse Distribution Association, 1971 (Box 5)
      - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1971 (Box 5)
      - American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronauts, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Converse College, 1971 (Box 6)
      - American Trucking Association, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Conservationists Luncheon, 1971 (Box 6)
      - GM Diesel of Canada, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Interview with Astronaut Al Worden, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Council of Engineering & Scientific Society of Secretaries, 1971 (Box 6)
      - International Association of Auto Theft Investigators, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Kettering Engineering and Scientific Center Dedication, 1971 (Box 6)
      - GM Girls Club Luncheon, 1971 (Box 6)
      - United Foundation Talk, 1971 (Box 6)
      - DuPoint Finishes Sales Meeting, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Michigan Automobile Deals Convention, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Interview, Jim Harper: Detroit Press, 1971 (Box 5)
      - DIT-MIT Luncheon, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Servicability and Interchangability, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Society of Manufacturing Engineers, 1971 (Box 6)
    - 1972
      - Ducks Unlimited, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Institutional Investors Conference, 1972 (Box 6)
      - YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit, 1972 (Box 6)
      - American Petroleum Institute, 1972 (Box 6)
      - International Oil Industry Meeting, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Alabama Safety Council, 1972 (Box 6)
      - GM Management Conference, 1972 (Box 6)
      - 1st International Congress on Automotive Safety, 1972 (Box 6)
      - GMI and Field Management Development Program, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Product Servicability and Interchangability Event, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Crusade of Mercy Campaign, 1972 (Box 6)
      - The Traffic Club of Pittsburgh, 1972 (Box 6)
      - National Defense Transportation Association, 1972 (Box 6)
      - William M. Walker Jr. Retirement, 1972 (Box 6)
      - University of Texas, 1972 (Box 6)
      - UM Society of Mechanical Engineers, 1972 (Box 7)
      - Detroit Institute of Technology, 1972 (Box 7)
      - The Explorers Club, 1972 (Box 7)
      - Frigidaire Meeting, 1972 (Box 7)
      - National Paint and Coatings Association Conference, 1972 (Box 7)
      - General Managers Meeting, 1972 (Box 7)
    - 1973
      - Cadillac Field Management Group, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Fraternal Order of Police, 1973 (Box 7)
      - National Computer Conference, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Commencement Address- Ferris State University, 1973 (Box 7)
      - 20th Anniversary, GM Training Center, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Industrial Relations Conference, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Delco Moraine Open House, 1973 (Box 7)
      - National Defense Transportation Association, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Bloomfield Hills High School, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Golden Jubilee Dinner, St. Mary's University, Texas, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Mayo Clinic, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Student Branch, SAE, University of Arizona, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Ribbon Cutting Ceremony, Pierce Chevrolet (RI), 1973 (Box 7)
      - Denver Rotary Club, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Advanced Management Seminar, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Automotive Organization Team, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Institutional Investors Conference, 1973 (Box 7)
      - GM Personnel Conference, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Industrial Waste Programs, 1973 (Box 7)
      - General Motors Institute, 1973 (Box 7)
      - San Diego GM Alumni Group, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Bob Lund Day, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Servicability & Interchangability Exhibit, 1973 (Box 7)
      - U-M Rotary Engine Seminar, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Environmental Activities Staff, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Detroit Rotary Club, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Kiawanas Club of San Diego, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Environmental Action Staff Seminar, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Detroit Institute of Technology, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Society of Plastic Engineers, 1973 (Box 8)
      - GM Award for Excellence Program, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Comptrollers Conference, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Cast Metals Federation Annual Meeting, 1973 (Box 8)
      - School of Modern Merchandising and Management, 1973 (Box 8)
      - International Marketing Congress, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Pontiac National Wholesale Meeting, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Misc Speeches, 1973-1976 (Box 8)
      - Honorary Doctorate- Saginaw Valley College, 1973 (Box 9)
      - Houston Chamber of Commerce, 1973 (Box 9)
    - 1974-1975
      - United Way of America, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Commencement Address, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Purchasing Management Association Executive Night, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Akron Rubber Group Meeting, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Management Policy Council, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Guide Lamp Ground Breaking Ceremonies, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Chemical Coatings Conference, 1974 (Box 8)
      - GM Management Conference, 1974 (Box 8)
      - International Air Cargo Forum, 1974 (Box 8)
      - World Aerospace Conference, 1974 (Box 8)
      - GM Institute Commencement, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Society of Automotive Engineers, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Bill Bossett Retirement Dinner, 1974 (Box 8)
      - GM Parts Division Dealer Conference, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Conference on Areas of Public Concern, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Chevrolet Dealers Management Group Meeting, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Motor Car Dealers Association of Southern California, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Puget Sound Engineering Council, 1974 (Box 9)
      - GM Parts Division Dealer Conference, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Farm Construction and Industrial Machinery, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Indiana University School of Business Conference, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Idaho Automobile Dealers Association Conference, 1974 (Box 9)
      - American Chemical Society, 1974 (Box 9)
      - GM Awards for Excellence Conference, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Midwest Business Administration Association, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Grand Rapids Rotary Club, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Committee of One Hundred, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Pontiac Motor Executive Conference, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Senior Men's Club of Detroit Athletic Club, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Detroit Regional Employers Institute for Cooperative Education, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Commencement Speech, Lawrence Institute of Technology, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Caltech Kick-Off Dinner, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Saginaw Steering Bear Kick-off, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Modern Management, Issues and Ideas, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Grosse Point Senior Men's Club, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Phil Donahue Program (Ralph Nader), 1974 (Box 9)
      - Lou Gordon Show, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Chevrolet 20 Group, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Detroit Management Conference, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Annual Sword of Mercy Dinner, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Automotive Market Research Council, 1975 (Box 9)
      - Misc Speeches, 1974-1975 (Box 9)
      - Misc Papers, undated (Box 9)
      - University of Detroit, Engineering Slide Rule Club, 1974 (Box 9)
      - Engineers Joint Council Annual Assembly, 1974 (Box 9)
  - Personal Materials, 1829-1997
    - Audio/Visual Recordings
      - GM Retirement, undated; 1 film reels (Box 16)
      - Nixon Victory Dinner, 1972; 1 audiotape (3 3/4 ips) (Box 13)
      - CBS Newsbreak: Ed Cole, A Very Special Person, 1977; 1 audiotape (Box 13)
      - Ed Cole Tribute, undated; 1 audiocassettes (Box 13)
      - Ed Cole Stories, undated; 1 videocassettes (U-Matic) (Box 13)
      - David Cole Engineering Lectures, 1972-1973; 1 videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 13)
        (Audiovisual materials)
      - National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism short films
        - "Good Old Harry", undated; 1 videotape (Box 13)
        - "Bill and Helen", undated; 1 videotape (Box 13)
        - "National Drinking Game", undated; 1 videotape (Box 13)
      - Trip to Central America: Guatemala, 1964; 1 film reels (Box 20)